Muhammad Ahmad

E: chaudryahmad21@gmail.com T: +92 313 6388056 LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/mahmad21/ Johar Town, Lahore

PERSONAL STATEMENT

I am a highly investigative Data Analyst; with three years of Freelance experience in Digital Marketing and Data Analytics and over a year of industry experience in Digital Marketing. I am capable of working within a team as well as leading a team. I have skills in SQL and Python for data cleansing and analysis along with Tableau and MS Excel for data visualization, dashboards, and reports. I am also very proficient in Social Media Marketing, Search Engine Marketing & Google Analytics. Apart from the technical skills, I have excellent written and verbal communication skills.

EDUCATION

Manchester Metropolitan University, Manchester, United Kingdom

MSc Project Management with Data Analytics

Sept 2019-Sept 2021

Dissertation: Data Analytics for Peer-to-Peer Energy Trading

Modules: Project Management Professional Practice, Computational Statistics and Visualization, Data Management and Machine Learning, etc.

Bahauddin Zakariya University, Multan, Pakistan

BS-IT (Information Technology)

Oct 2013-Oct 2017

Dissertation: Store Automation System (A web software to manage inventory for faculty)

Modules: Probability and Statistics, Data Structures and Algorithm, Data Warehousing and Data Mining, RDMS using Oracle, JAVA, etc.

PROFESSIONAL WORK EXPERIENCE

Digital Marketing Coach (DigiSkills Training Program)

July 2018-Oct 2019

Worked as a Digital Marketing Coach at DigiSkills Training Program in Lahore, Pakistan. Responsibilities:

- To provide assistance and resolve trainee queries via chat, e-mail, and phone.
- To assist in course video production and review all course related content.
- To develop and assess course related content.

Received an Appreciation Letter from Project Director for taking responsibility of General and Technical Support duties.

Data Analytics and Marketing (Remote)

Worked as Digital Marketer and Data Analyst at RA Aesthetics Training Academy in Manchester, UK.

Initially started as Digital Marketer and moved to the position of Junior Data Analyst.

Sep 2020-Nov 2021

Responsible for running and managing Facebook and Instagram ads, along with analysis of internal data using MS Excel with the in-house analytics team and website analysis using Google Analytics.

FREELANCE PROJECTS

Digital Marketing and Website Development

2017-2019

Worked with several clients on Facebook as a Digital Marketer and WordPress website developer. Developed websites using WordPress CMS for clients, setup social media and Google ad campaigns to increase sales and perform website analysis.

Google Analytics 2018-2020

Managing and tracking customer data using Google Analytics, analyzing website traffic to improve search engine optimization (SEO), provide statistics for forecasting and conversion tracking.

Masters:

Dissertation: Data Analytics for Peer-to-peer Energy Trading

July 2021

Developed a distributed P2P energy trading model based on data analytics applications. I proposed several ideas such as:

- A framework for energy sharing system where DSO is integrated with microgrids and independent energy providers within those microgrids.
- Big data analytics application with energy generation and consumption analysis and forecasting on real-life datasets from London smart meters in the UK and used Time series & ARIMA models to train my dataset.
- Data analytics and prediction model designed to combine time and weather data and predict accurate energy generation and consumption results with time granularity of hourly, weekly, and monthly.

Project Scheduling, Finance and Resource Management

Nov 2019

A case study on Scottish Parliament Building project, recommendations on how they could have avoided the mistakes by establishing a proper communication link and reduce construction costs by doing a detailed risk analysis.

Statistical Analysis and Data Visualization using SAS

Dec 2019

Data Analysis and visualization of real-world data by producing Boxplots, Histograms, Confidence and Prediction Intervals.

Performed Machine Learning Algorithms using Data Mining Approach in WEKA

Feb 2020

Data Pre-processing: Data cleaning, Data Transformation and Data Discretization.

Algorithms: Support Vector Machine (SVM), Feature Selection, Random Forest, and Decision Trees.

Bachelors:

RDBMS using oracle March 2017

Worked on RDBMS project using oracle for my semester final project.

Developed an Android application

May 2016

Worked as a front-end developer, UI/UX of the application, also worked on some functionality of the application, responsible for the compatibility with different devices.

A fully functional website

Dec 2015

A fully functional website using HTML/CSS, JavaScript and PHP as my semester final project and worked on Wamp server for the server-side functionality.

SKILLS SUMMARY LANGUAGE

Skills	Intermediate	Advanced	Expert
SQL & Python for Data Cleansing		\	
and Analysis		•	
Tableau for Data Visualization,		\	
Dashboards & Reports		•	
Microsoft Excel			\
Digital Marketing & Analytics			/
(SMM/SEM/Google Analytics)			·
Project Management	~		
Written and Oral			✓
Communication			•

Language	Speaking Only	Professional (Written and speaking fluency)
English		~
Urdu		~
Punjabi	>	